<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foure summons of the Shulamite A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse vpon Rogation Sunday, the 5. of May. 1605. By John Rawlinson, Bachelor of Diuinitie, and fellow of Saint Iohns Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847269</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847269</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10497)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1581:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foure summons of the Shulamite A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse vpon Rogation Sunday, the 5. of May. 1605. By John Rawlinson, Bachelor of Diuinitie, and fellow of Saint Iohns Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne, by Simon Waterson [in London],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's address from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages cropped, stained and tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOVRE SVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS OF THE <hi>SHVLAMITE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Sermon preached at Pauls Croſse vpon Rogation Sunday, the</hi> 5. <hi>of</hi> May. 1605.</p>
            <p>By JOHN RAWLINSON, Bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of Divinitie, and fellow of Saint Iohns Colledge in Oxford.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The morning commeth, and alſo the night. Jf yee will ſeeke, ſeeke: returne, and come.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Iſai. 21.12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne, by <hi>Simon Waterſon,</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my purpoſe <hi>(Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader)</hi> that theſe my ſory labours ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue ſlept in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ben buried in the <hi>Church-yard</hi> where firſt they were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, then by a ſecond publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (more publike) haue ſtoode to the mercie of many mercileſſe <hi>Cenſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure J am, it had ben my ſafer and ſurer way, to haue practiſed the policie of <hi>Antony</hi> in <hi>Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicer. orat. pro Cluen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who woulde never make his pen <hi>publike-Notarie</hi> to his tongue, that if ought had at any time fallen from him ſuperfluous or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, hee might ſafely denie that to haue ben ſpoken, which written hee could not ſo ſoundly warrant:</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, conſidering the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe times: wherein <hi>VVriters,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:12298:3"/>
               <hi>Readers</hi> are both too-blame. For as there is more than Gods plenty of <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> ſuch as are at <hi>Davids Dico ego ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra mea Regi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> before they can ſaie with <hi>David, Eructavit cor meum verbum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> More carefull to provide a vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patron for their worke, than a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worke worthy the Patronage: and ſo combring the Preſſe with froathy &amp; worthles Pamphlets, that had it voice, it would hideouſly roare and cry, like a man now almoſt preſſt to death: <hi>More weight; for the loue of god, more weight: more weight in your matter, but leſse of your paper.</hi> So is there a marveilous pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of <hi>Readers,</hi> (ſuch as are wel &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably affected;) inſomuch that fevve there are of the more ingenuous ſorte, <hi>Qui malint eloquendo culpam deprecari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quàm tacendo culpâ vacare:</hi> who had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by divulging their endevors craue a curteous pardon; than by ſuppreſſing them be out of gunſhot of cavill &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; the very quinteſſence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens learning being nothing but a
<pb facs="tcp:12298:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>carping at other mens labors; and yet ſome of thoſe many ſuch, as I know had rather preach 20. Sermons, than print one, leaſt their filching and purloining ſhould be tracked and detected.</p>
            <p>But the Reaſons that haue vvrought me, thus to venture vpon the ſharpe of this ages cenſure, are chiefly two;</p>
            <p>One, The inceſſant <hi>importunity</hi> of friends, to whom J may ſay as <hi>Paulinus</hi> doth to his vpon like occaſion:<note place="margin">Paul. epiſt. <hi>9</hi> ad Sulpit. Sever.</note> 
               <hi>Sibi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putet famem, qui pauperis amici forem pulſat, &amp; promptuariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inane ſcrutatur.</hi> Let him thanke himſelfe, if hee be ſent away hungry, who knocks as the dore of his poore friend, and rifles his empty cupbord for victuals.</p>
            <p>Another, The inſtant <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of theſe daies (theſe laſt, &amp; evill daies) the ſores wherof run and ceaſe not, becauſe the ſinnes thereof cry, &amp; ſtent not; that by a deepe and diligent conſideration of the many ſaving leſſons herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the men of this generation may vnfeignedly and effectually turne from
<pb facs="tcp:12298:4"/>their wicked waies, and ſo turne awaie from them, and from this whole Land the angry viols of Gods dreadfull ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, the dregs wherof elſe they are likely to ſucke vp.</p>
            <p>Theſe (with other the like) reaſons, haue ſomuch the rather prevailed with me, becauſe I am for ſurety give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that there paſſe abroad for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſome maimed and diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, (ſuch as were curſorily taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mouth) which J knowe not how far forth they may turne to my preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: And haue cauſed me to republiſh this Sermon,<note place="margin">Ioan. 11.44</note> like a <hi>Lazarus rediuinus,</hi> newly riſen out of the <hi>graue</hi> of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, bound about not with <hi>napkins,</hi> but with <hi>paper-ſheets;</hi> to preach not <hi>Viuâ v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> with any liuelyhood of voice as before (which yet is the chiefe grace &amp; verniſh of a Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) but with a dead &amp; black letter: A killing letter to thoſe that will not turne, but a quickening letter to the penitent <hi>Conuert;</hi> That what then was ſounded forth in the
<pb facs="tcp:12298:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>eares of a Great and Honorable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (the very confluence of the whole Land) may now ſubiect it ſelfe likewiſe to the eies, aſwell of the then abſent, as of thoſe that were preſent:<note place="margin">Aug. tract. de Epicur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stoic. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vt neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes inſtruantur, ſcientes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur: illi cognoſcant, illi recognoſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> that the ignorant may be inſtructed, the learned admoniſhed, that the one may learne what his duty is, the other recognize what he hath learned:</p>
            <p>That what then was confined with in the ſpace of two houres, may now be <hi>Omnium horarum:</hi> A ſermon for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very houre:</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God) was thought fruitfull to many, may now (by the ſame bleſſing) become profitable to all. It ſhal then be thy part <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> (ſuch as it is) to take it in good part, naked, and (J think) <hi>Verbatìm</hi> as it was vttered: as imparted vnto thee to no worſe end, than to make thee partaker of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aſpect, which is promiſed (&amp; ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:12298:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo haue ben ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled) in the ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral part of my <hi>Text,</hi> had not the time intercepted my diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſhal aſke (as in ſuch a world of <hi>Buſybodies,</hi> many of liklyhood will) what the reaſon might be, that albeit I ſerue a Right-worthily Great &amp; eminent Father of the Church, the Lorde Biſhop of London, (ſole prop and pillar of my hopes and fortunes) to whome as (in parte) J owe to the very prime beginnings of that ſmal preferment which J haue (which ſince he hath alſo ſeconded by many grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous encouragments:) ſo J wholy vow <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very vtmoſt mite of my poore ſeruice: Yet J ſend forth this Sermon into the world, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior did his diſciples,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſine baculo et perâ:</hi> without either <hi>the ſtaffe</hi> of protection, or <hi>the ſcrip</hi> of dedication wherwith to beg patronage; My anſwere is ready, that as <hi>Minimum maximi maius est maximo minimi.</hi> The leaſt of that which is greateſt is more than the greateſt of
<pb facs="tcp:12298:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the leaſt: ſo the leaſt of his fauours is more then the greateſt of my deſarts: and to preſent his Greatnes with ſo ſmall a <hi>preſent,</hi> were but <hi>aſsem Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanto dare:</hi> as J may ſay,<note place="margin">Macrob. Sat. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> to giue a <hi>dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to a Monarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue therfore choſen rather to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it as a poore patronleſſe <hi>Orphan,</hi> that ſo it may happily meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Patrons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide. Pag. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> J am ſure one part of it hath already met with ſome.</p>
            <p>Or if it proue ſo infortunate, to haue none to patronize it, yet my truſt is that God <hi>(the father of Orphans)</hi> will accept it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.5.</note> To whoſe bleſſed protection J commit both it and thee: as my ſelfe &amp; al my ſtudies to thy godly and dayly prayers: reciprocally prayeng vnto God, for thee, and thy ſouls good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> JOHN RAWLINSON.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohns Coll. in Oxon.</hi> 
                  <date>Ian. 10.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12298:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FOVRE SVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS OF THE <hi>SHVLAMITE.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Returne, returne ô Shulamite: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, returne that we may behold thee.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Cant. 6. ver. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His golden book of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticles (Right Honorable, Right worſhipfull, and right dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Mirror of loue Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus)</hi> endited by the wiſeſt <hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; for the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of it aboue other Songs, by ſome entitled <hi>Canticum Canticorum,</hi> A <hi>ſong of ſongs:</hi> by others <hi>Cantica Canticoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> The <hi>ſongs of ſongs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo Cardi. pref. in Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> becauſe (as <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> yeilds the reaſon) <hi>&amp; vnum est, &amp; multa;</hi> it is both one, &amp; manie;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12298:7"/>One, if we regard the vnity of the dity<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the purport and tenor wherof is Loue which is the very bond of vnity: &amp; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manie, if we regard the variety of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Singers, which are foure: (the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome,</hi> and his <hi>Bride:</hi> the <hi>Friends of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bridegrome,</hi> and the <hi>Companions of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bride</hi>) is not carnally, but ſpiritually; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> literally, but myſticallie; not properlie but figuratiuely to be vnderſtood.</p>
            <p>For it is not as ſome phanaticall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits, (deriders &amp; deſpighters of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace) haue no leſſe calumniouſly than blaſphemouſly tearmed it, <hi>A laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious Ballad, or wanton Sonnet,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Solomon</hi> would court, and currie favour with his <hi>Concubine:</hi> But it is (as <hi>Nicolaus de Lyrâ</hi> cals it) <hi>Epithalamicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Carmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nicolaus de Lyrâ in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> A ſpirituall <hi>Mariage-ſong:</hi> wherin is moſt graphically painted out vnto vs, that ſound, perfit, and vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Loue, wherwith our Savior Chriſt (a Greater &amp; wiſer than <hi>Salomon</hi>) doth dialogue-wiſe, and by entercourſe of ſpeach, woo his wandring ſpouſe, <hi>the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12298:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfull ſoule:</hi> not onlie calling her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe come vnto him, but eft ſoones recalling her, when ſhee is parted from him.</p>
            <p>Yet no where, either in this, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other booke of Scripture, doth hee more ſignificantly &amp; emphatically vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſtrong and vehement affection towards her, than in the wordes of my Text:</p>
            <q>Returne, returne, O Shulamite: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, returne, that wee may beholde thee.</q>
            <p>Shee was gone a nutting into the <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of nuts,</hi> ver. 10. <hi>and to ſee the fruites of the valley, to ſee if the vine budded, and if the pome-granats flouriſhed:</hi> that is, ſhee was wholy ſet vpon her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and minded nothing but tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie delights.</p>
            <p>Leſt therefore by proceeding in the purſuit of ſuch vanities, ſhe might hap to looſe her ſelfe in the garden of nuts, as <hi>Adam</hi> loſt himſelfe in the garden of apples: our Saviour,<note place="margin">Gen 3.17.</note> euen in an extaſie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12298:8"/>of loue, here follows and as it were hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la's after her, once and againe, &amp; twiſe againe:</p>
            <q>Returne, returne, O Shulamite: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, returne, that wee may behold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee:</q>
            <p>That ſo, in fine, if not his loue, yet his importunity might reduce her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her garden to his paradiſe: from her ſweets which were tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſient to his bliſſe which is permanent: from the iawes of hell to the ioies of heaven: from the Onyons of Aegypt to the Manna of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: from the captivity of Babylon to the libertie of Sion: from the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fleſh to the puritie of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: from the by way of error to the high-way of truth: and from the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ignorance to the brightneſſe of knowledge.</p>
            <p>Here then by the <hi>Shulamite</hi> is tropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally meant, the ſoule of euery faithful man, who is lapſed and fallen into any kind of infirmity: or (which in effect is all one) The Church of Chriſt, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12298:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereof (by ſin) haue made a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from God.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>reduplication,</hi> or <hi>often repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> of this one word: <hi>Returne;</hi> ſhe is ſummoned to that <hi>vnum neceſſarium,</hi> that onely neceſſary duty of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance: which if ſhe performe as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, as it is ſeriouſly enioined her, it will preſent her pure and blameleſſe, without ſpot or wrinckle, blot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in the ſight of her huſband.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Beholding,</hi> is ſignified both Gods <hi>Approbation</hi> and notice of her, who as he beholdeth the proud a far of, Pſal: 138: so hath he reſpect vnto the lowly: As alſo her <hi>Reprobation</hi> of herſelfe, who as by turning her back to Chriſt, ſhe loſt the view of him (that glaſſe which reflected her to herſelfe) ſo by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning back againe vnto him, ſhe is brought to a due &amp; diligent conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration aſwel of what ſhe was before ſhe plaied the fugitiue, as of her preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being now become <hi>a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the church of Chriſt, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12298:9"/>
               <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. is called <hi>Hortus concluſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 4.12.</note> An incloſed garden, may fitly be reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that ancient paradiſe, wherin our firſt parents firſt planted by God were after ſupplanted by the ſerpent.<note place="margin">Gen. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For as it was watered with foure ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>(Piſhon Gihon, Hiddekel, &amp; Perah)</hi> which refreſhed al the trees therof, and cauſed them to fructifie, among which was the <hi>tree of the knowledge of good &amp; euil:</hi> ſo the Church is here watred with the ſweeteſt voice of her ſpouſe Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe voice is <hi>Tanquam vox a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarum multarum</hi> as the voice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters,<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. euen as the voice of 4. <hi>Riuers</hi> (4. Riuers of repentant teares) here ſhadowed by a foure-fold returne: which beſides other fruites wil bring forth in her the fruit of the knowledge of good &amp; euil: wherof no ſooner ſhal ſhe taſte, but her eies wil by &amp; by be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and ſhe ſhal behold her ſelfe: Yea her friends, (the bleſſed company of Angels) wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behold her, &amp; behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her triumph in her converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12298:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the whole trinity will then behold her as the worke of their owne hands, and therfore Chriſt her ſpouſe muſt needs behold her, as the louely wife of his owne boſome.</p>
            <q>Returne, returne ô Shulamite, returne, returne that we may behold thee.</q>
            <p>The words ſhed themſelues into two parts.</p>
            <p>The one, <hi>An admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or Inuitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other, <hi>A Reaſon, or Inſtigation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hath in it 3 things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our obſeruation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>Matter, or tenor</hi> of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition; Returne.</item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Forme, or manner</hi> of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition;
A double-double iteration <hi>of it.</hi>
                  <q>Returne, returne, returne, returne.</q>
               </item>
               <item>3 The <hi>Partie admoniſhed;</hi> the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſon,</hi> though at a bluſh it ſeem to be but one, yet indeed <hi>Incluſiuè,</hi> by way of implication it is 3-fold, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the 3-fold ſenſe which it beareth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12298:10"/>importing a 3-fold benefit.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That we may behold thee:</hi> that is,</p>
            <p>That my father, my ſelfe, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt (all three perſons of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) may caſt a fauorable aſpect on thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That we may behold thee:</hi> that is,</p>
            <p>That my ſelfe, with the reſt of thy friends and wel-willers (euen the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſociety of Angels) may reſpect thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>That we may behold thee:</hi> that is,</p>
            <p>That both J thy redeemer may look vpon thee with a fatherly and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate eie of mercy: &amp; that thou maiſt alſo looke into thy ſelfe with a ſincere &amp; ſingle eie of ſimplicity.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>liſts and land-marks,</hi> wherewith at this time J muſt bound the <hi>proceſſion</hi> of my diſcourſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt then to begin with the <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,</hi> and therin firſt with the <hi>Matter</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Returne:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hebritians</hi> wel tell you, that the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall word which the Vulgar Latin here renders <hi>Reuertere,</hi> Returne; is alſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12298:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>rendered <hi>Convertere,</hi> Be thou conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And ſo reades both S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Virginibus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. lib. <hi>3</hi> de Virgeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hiero. Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ad Algaſ.</note> &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Epiſtle ad <hi>Algaſiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this reading being Paſſiue, doth (mee thinkes) better diſcypher vnto vs the ground of our repentance, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth the former, which is Actiue. <hi>Nos enim non tam agimus, quam à Deo agimur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zanchius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanchius.</note> For we are not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid to doe good, as to be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to doe it, by the good ſpirit of God. And the Apoſtle tels vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. That it is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but in God that ſheweth mercy: <hi>Non quia velle, &amp; currere no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de. bemus</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auſtin) <hi>ſed quia ipſe in nobis &amp; velle operatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; currere:</hi> Not that we are exempted from willing, &amp; ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, but becauſe it is God that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs both to wil, and to run. For we can no more run vp the hill of God which is mount Sion (the mount of bliſſe) vnleſſe wee be ſet on running by the finger of Gods ſpirit, than a ſtone
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12298:11"/>of it ſelfe can run downe a hill, without ſome impulſiue powre to ſet it on run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>True it is, that Chriſtianity is not a licentious, or a Libertine-like ſecuritie: but a warring and agonizing trade of life, a preſſing toward the marke, a ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to enter in at the narrow gate, a day-labor for a penny, &amp; a violent ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing of the kingdome of heauen: and that Chriſtians <hi>ſpiritu Dei agunt,</hi> what good they do, they do by the ſpirite of God: But withal it's as true, that as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are the ſonnes of God, <hi>ſpiritu Dei aguntur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. are led by the ſpirit of God: and it is the bountifulnes of that ſpirite which leads vs to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That vvhich <hi>David</hi> ſaith of man as touching his naturall life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.40.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. that he is <hi>ſpiritus vadens, &amp; non rediens,</hi> A ſpirit that paſſeth away, and commeth not againe, is no leſſe true as touching his ſpiritual life. He is <hi>ſpiritus vadens e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non rediens:</hi> A ſpirit that paſſeth awai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12298:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and commeth not againe. He paſſeth away from God of himſelfe, but of him ſelfe he cannot returne againe.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt the rod out of his hand <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. it was turned into a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:<note place="margin">Exod 4.3</note> but no ſooner did he put his hand to the taile of the ſerpent, but it by &amp; by turned againe into a rod: So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God as it were caſts vs of for our ſinns, we are turned into ſerpents, even a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vipers,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Matt.</hi> 3. ſpawnes of that old Serpent the <hi>Diuell:</hi> but when once it pleaſeth God to reach forth the hand of his grace vnto vs, then are we turned againe into a <hi>rod,</hi> and may ſay with <hi>Dauid pſal:</hi> 74.<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.3.</note> 
               <hi>Redemiſti virgam haereditatis tuae.</hi> Thou haſt redeemd the <hi>rod,</hi> or (as our Engliſh hath it) the <hi>tribe</hi> of thine inheritance.</p>
            <p>Let not vs then <hi>(my deare and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)</hi> who of our ſelues are not able ſomuch as to think a good thought think ſo wel of our ſelues, that we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (as of our ſelues) to returne to God, but in a true ſenſe and feeling of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12298:12"/>owne inſufficiency, let vs pray with the <hi>prophet Ieremy</hi> Lament. 5.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>Conuerte nos domine ad te, et co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uertemur.</hi> Turne thou vs vnto thee, o Lord, and we ſhall be turned.</p>
            <p>This briefly by occaſion of the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue</hi> reading of this word Returne: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere,</hi> Be thou conuerted.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in our Returne are 5. which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe J haue many things to ſay vnto you, J will rather touch, or taſt, than handle.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The firſt, is <hi>Terminus a quo. whence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Terminus ad quem wither,</hi> or to <hi>whome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Tempus in guo: when.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Modus quo. How.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Medium per good, which way.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>whence, whether, when, How, and which way,</hi> theſe be the 5 <hi>circumſtances</hi> to be conſidered in our returne.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: If you aſke me, whence you muſt returne; J anſwere, from the crooked &amp; wicked waves of the <hi>world</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12298:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the miry, and dirty waies of the <hi>fleſh:</hi> from the dangerous, &amp; thieuiſh waies of the <hi>Diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Geneſ:</hi> 12. the Lord giues this commandement vnto <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee out of thine owne country, &amp; from thy kinred, &amp; from thy fathers houſe:</hi> So muſt all that will be the Sons of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> get them out of their owne country, that is the world, &amp; their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is the fleſh: and their fathers houſe, that is the houſe of the Diuell.</p>
            <p>When the Lord inuites them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto him, they muſt not excuſe themſelues as they did <hi>Luc:</hi> 14.<note place="margin">Luk. 14.18.</note> J haue bought a farme, &amp; J muſt needes goe ſee it: the <hi>farme</hi> is the world. Or J haue maried a wife, and cannot come: the <hi>wife</hi> is the fleſh: or J haue bought fiue yoke of Oxen &amp; J muſt goe proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the <hi>fiue yoke of Oxen</hi> is the Divell, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was aſked his name, called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>Legion,</hi> or a multitude. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Luk. 8.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If you aſke me <hi>whither,</hi> or <hi>to whom</hi> you muſt returne: J anſwere,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12298:13"/>Not with the Sow to her wallow, not with the dog to his vomit,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 2.22.</note> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. that is, not to thoſe ſinnes, from which yee haue once ben pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by repentance, &amp; which yee haue vomited out by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: but to God alone, who (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Austin</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>Revocat errantes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. medit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat repugnantes, expectat torpentes, amplexatur redeuntes;</hi> Recalleth them that wander, inviteth them that reſiſt, expecteth them that linger, &amp; embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them that returne.</p>
            <p>O Jſrael, if thou returne, returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ierem 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ierem.</hi> 4. <hi>Vnto me,</hi> ſaith the Lord: <hi>Quales ad qualem?</hi> ſaith <hi>Hugo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hug. de S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictor.</note> what manner of men to vvhat manner of God? <hi>Clauſi ad oſtium, aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ad medicum, nauſ ragi ad portum.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ye that are priſoners, to mee that am the dore, ye that are ſick, to me that am the Phyſition, ye that ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrecke, to me that am the hauen. The dore that giveth libertie, the Phyſition that giveth health, and the hauen that giveth ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12298:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thirdly, Jf you aſke me, when you muſt returne: I anſwere, not to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or here-after, but <hi>to day. Heb.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.15.</note> For behold now the accepted time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now the day of ſalvation. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Now</hi> is that <hi>Tempus putationis,</hi> that time of pruning, ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of by the ſpouſe <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. But hereafter is <hi>Tempus ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.12.</note> a time not of pruning, but of cutting down. Now muſt we cut of the ſuperfluities of our ſins, with the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning knife of repentance, els wil Chriſt hereafter be ſure to cut vs downe with the axe of iudgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Now is <hi>Tempus tuum,</hi> thy time, the time which God hath lent thee for thine amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: (&amp; therefore <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the righteous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a tree which brings forth fruit <hi>In tempore ſuo,</hi> in his owne time:) But hereafter it is not thy time, but Gods time: Not <hi>Dies hominis,</hi> mans day; but <hi>Dies Domini,</hi> the day of the Lord, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. O giue thanks vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.1.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12298:14"/>for he is gracious, <hi>Quoniam in ſaeculum miſericordia eius,</hi> becauſe his mercie endureth for euer:<note place="margin">Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. ibid.</note> Videte quid dicat; <hi>In ſaeculum ait</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierom</hi>) Mark what he ſaith, He ſaith for an age, or for ever: that is, for ever during the time of our preſent life. <hi>In inferno, autem quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitebitur domino?</hi> But who wil, nay who can giue thee thanks in the pit?<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Our aduerſaries may dreame of a Purgatory-penance, yet indeed after death there is no repentance. O then now giue thankes, or now confeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, becauſe he is never merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful but now; <hi>Hic miſericors, illic index eſt;</hi> Jn this life hee is a mercifull father, but in the other life he will be a terrible iudge.<note place="margin">Damaſ. ſerm de defunct.</note> And (as <hi>Damaſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> excellently ſpeakes) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Its too late to come to bargaine, when the fare is once diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The other life is (as we ſay) a daie after the fare. Jts therefore then too late to ſue for mercy.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtrange it is to ſee, how as if the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12298:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>fare of this life, and the <hi>tabernacle</hi> of our fleſh ſhould neuer be diſſolued, nay as if we hoped by da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing daliance to get the kingdome of God, as <hi>Herod</hi> promiſed the daughter of <hi>Herodias,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the halfe of his kingdom for a dance <hi>Mark.</hi> 6. we procraſtinate our returne to God.<note place="margin">Mark. 6.23. Gen. 8.7.</note> And like <hi>Noahs crow, Gen:</hi> 8. tyring vpon the rotten carrion of ſome earthly delight, we care not for retiring back to God the Arke of our ſtrength. And wheras we ſhould haue <hi>vocem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the voice of a doue, mourning for our ſinnes like good <hi>Ezechias, Eſa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 38.14.</note> 38. our voice is <hi>vox corvina,</hi> the voice of a crow, crying nothing but <hi>Cras, cras.</hi> to morow, and to morow, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good morows:<note place="margin">Exod. 8.10.</note> like <hi>Pharao Exod</hi> 8. who when <hi>Moſes</hi> bad him commande when he ſhould pray for him, anſwered <hi>Cras,</hi> to morow: Not conſidering that as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith. <hi>Manet foris cum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce corvinaâ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>qui non habet ſimplicitatem columbinam,</hi> He ſhall ſtand without dores with his crows voice, who hath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12298:15"/>not in him the doues ſimplicity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Jf you aſke me how yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt returne, J anſwere, <hi>Non paſsib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> corporis, ſed paſſionibus cordis:</hi> Not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the paces of the body, but by the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; affections of the hatt: even <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.12.</note> with al your hart; as it is <hi>Ioel.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The fathers call the affections <hi>Ped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> animae,</hi> the feet of the ſoule. We mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therfore be ſure to look wel to our fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eccle:</hi> 4. and to ſee that our affectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> runne all one way,<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.17.</note> all of them towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. For <hi>wo to the ſinner that goeth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> manner of waies:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>Eccle:</hi> 2. whoſe affe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions run ſome of them to <hi>God-war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſome towards <hi>Mammon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> 
               <hi>Matt:</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Jt is noted of <hi>Pilat Ioan:</hi> 18. that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> asked our Sauiour this queſtion,<note place="margin">Ioan. 18.38.</note> 
               <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt veritas?</hi> what is the truth? But h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had no ſooner aſked the queſtion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he preſently went forth again vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iews</hi> without his anſwere.</p>
            <p>What was this but to come hoppin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as it were to God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one foot, &amp; wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> another to hopp back againe to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12298:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>He made the queſtion, but he ſtaid not for his anſwere. The world is now adaies full of ſuch <hi>Queſtioniſts,</hi> whoſe deuotion is like an Aſſes gallup, ſoone at an end. They demand with <hi>Pilat,</hi> what is the truth? while they are turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto God by deſire of verity, but they are gone ere their anſwere come, while they are turned from God by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of vanity.</p>
            <p>Fiftly &amp; laſtly: Jf you aſke me which way you muſt returne J anſwere <hi>Per via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae,</hi> by the way (the ſtreight &amp; narow way) of repentance: of which it is ſaid <hi>Eſa:</hi> 30. <hi>This is the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 30.12.</note> 
               <hi>walk in it.</hi> This though it be <hi>via anfractuoſa</hi> (<hi>as S. Bernard ſpeakes</hi> in his declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) a hard,<note place="margin">Bernard. in declam.</note> a rough and a craggy way, yet is it not <hi>via infructuoſa,</hi> an inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, or a fruitleſſe waie, but the iſſues thereof are eternall life.</p>
            <p>Eor as ſinn is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an Auerſion,</hi> or the way by which wee turne from God: ſo repentance is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or the way, by which we returne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12298:16"/>to God: So that the way by which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> returne from God, is one, &amp; the way by which we returne againe to God, is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>There is the ſame way (ſaith <hi>Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totel</hi>) from <hi>Thebes to Athens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> from <hi>Athens</hi> to <hi>Thebes:</hi> (as we would ſay from <hi>London to Oxford,</hi> and from <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to London</hi>) yet doubtleſſe it is not the ſame way from heauen to hell, &amp; from hell to heauen. But as the man of God,<note place="margin">1. King. 13.9</note> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13. was charged not to returne back by the way that he cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Bethel:</hi> and the wiſemen that came to ſee Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Matt:</hi> 2. returned into their country another way than they came; So wee that departed from God by the high-way of pride, muſt returne to him againe by the lower waie of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie: wee that loſt him by the way of ſinne, muſt recover him againe by the way of repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugo de S. Victore</hi> hath expreſſt it thus;<note place="margin">Hugo de S. Victore.</note> Man (ſaith he) at firſt was ſo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, that he might haue proceeded <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bono
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12298:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae per bonum obedientiae ad bonum gloriae:</hi> from the good of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, by the good of obedience, to the good of glorie. But changing his ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and forſaking his innocencie, he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proceeded, <hi>De malo iniquitatis per malum mortalitatis ad malum dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis:</hi> from the evill of iniquitie, by the evil of mortalitie, to the evill of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Then came our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and ſhewed him another way, by which he muſt returne to his own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which is aboue. <hi>Per bonum paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae, &amp; bonum iuſtitiae, ad bonum glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae;</hi> by the good of repentance, &amp; the good of righteouſneſſe, to the good of glorie.</p>
            <p>Now leſt wee ſhould hap to miſtake the way, and thinke our ſelues in, when we are out: as they doe that afflict their ſoule for a daie, &amp; hang down the head like a <hi>bulruſh,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Eſay ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Eſa.</hi> 58.<note place="margin">Eſa. 58.5.</note> and after returne again to their old bias; like lazie houſe-wiues, that ſtrew the houſe with <hi>bulruſhes</hi> ere
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12298:17"/>they haue ſwept out the duſt: we muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know,<note place="margin">Luther.</note> that as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, <hi>Noua vita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> optima paenitentia:</hi> A newe life, is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſt repentance; and the onely true <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion</hi> is a new <hi>converſation.</hi> Whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> J take it to be, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> haue thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſignifie both <hi>conuerſion, &amp; conuerſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a true rule in Philoſophy, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Corruptio vnius eſt generatio alteriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one thing is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of another. And it is as true i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diuinity, that <hi>Mortificatio vnius eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vificatio alterius</hi> the mortifieng of the fleſh is the quickening of the ſpirit. The ſpirit cannot be quickened till the fleſh be mortified, nor the new man inherit, till the old man be dead.</p>
            <p>One compares the hart of man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>two-leafed book,</hi> wherin a man readeth all his owne workes. In one leafe read ſinners: Jn the other read the truly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. The ſinner reads thus: <hi>Haec ego egi, recordor, et delector:</hi> Theſe things haue J done, &amp; the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12298:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>is pleaſing vnto me. The penitent reads thus: <hi>Ego egi haec, recordor, et doleo:</hi> theſe things haue J done, &amp; the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of them is grieuous vnto me. We muſt not then ſtand poaring vpon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer leaſe, till we be euen poare-blinde with ſin: but we muſt turne ouer a new leafe, that is, we muſt lead a new life: <hi>Sic plangentes commiſsa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. flor. li. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt non commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus plangenda,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting for ſins committed, that we afterwards commit not ſinnes to be lamented.</p>
            <p>For as the <hi>ordinary Gloſs</hi> obſerues vpon <hi>Matt:</hi> 19. that a <hi>Camel</hi> could not enter into that gate at <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ ordin. in Matt. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> which for the ſtreightnes of it was called <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramen acus,</hi> The ey of a needle, <hi>Niſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito onere, et flexis genibus:</hi> till he had laid downe his burden, and bowed his knees: No more can we enter into the gate of the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) which for the ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, is compared to a Needls eie <hi>Matt:</hi> 19.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.24.</note> till we haue caſt of the heauy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12298:18"/>burdens of our ſins, and bowed euen the knees of our harts vnto God, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing pardon &amp; remiſſion of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>This of the firſt thing to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the <hi>Admonition,</hi> namely the <hi>Matter, or Tenor</hi> of it, <hi>Returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>Forme,</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> of the <hi>Admonition:</hi> which is <hi>a doubling &amp; redoubling of it: Returne, returne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherin (as in a map) is ſet before vs, the <hi>Clemency</hi> of God, the <hi>Contumacy</hi> of man: the <hi>Gratiouſnes</hi> of God, the <hi>Graceleſnes</hi> of man: the <hi>willingnes</hi> of God, the <hi>wilfulnes</hi> of man: God often calling man to returne; man ſtill neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the call of God.</p>
            <p>Here haue we one depth calling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; The depth of God to the the depth of man: The depth of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the depth of ignorance: The depth of mercy to the depth of miſery.</p>
            <p>He that is <hi>Sanctus, ſanctus, ſanctus,</hi> Holy,<note place="margin">Eſa. 6.3.</note> holy, holy, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6. crieth vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:12298:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>who is but <hi>Terra, terra, terra,</hi> Earth, earth, earth: <hi>Ierem:</hi> 22.<note place="margin">Iere. 22.29.</note> And what doth he cry? <hi>Returne, returne, returne.</hi> And why returne? becauſe otherwiſe (as he threatneth, <hi>Ezec.</hi> 21. He will <hi>ouerturne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 21.27</note> 
               <hi>ouerturne, ouerturne,</hi> as our Engliſh tranſlation hath it: but the vulgar Latin reads it, <hi>Iniquitatem iniquitatem, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatem ponam eam.</hi> that is as much to ſay, Our Iniquity ſhalbe our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
            <p>Nay, here are <hi>foure Returnes</hi> to three <hi>Ouerturnes:</hi> to ſhew, that as <hi>Iohn</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. 20.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20. ſo the mercy of Chriſt outſtripps his iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Chriſt coms vnto vs, not to aſke <hi>a Grace for a degree</hi> of vs (as we ſpeake in our vniuerſities) but to offer vs the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry higheſt degree of his grace:</hi> &amp; though wee deny it a firſt, ſecond, and third time, yet he corns vnto vs againe with a <hi>Supplicat quartò:</hi> He puts vp as it were a ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or a requeſt to the whole <hi>Congregation of his people,</hi> that yet at the fourth time, they would not deny it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:12298:19"/>
Here's precept vpon precept, and line vpon line; mercy vpon mercy, and mercy vpon mercy: becauſe as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith. <hi>His mercy endureth for ever, His mercy endureth for ever, His mercy endureth for ever.</hi> It is the ſweet <hi>burden</hi> or the 136.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 136.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme; ſeuen and twenty times</hi> repeated in that <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is a rule of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon civility among me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>Si ter pulſanti nemo reſpondet, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> Jf after thrice knocking no man ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thee, its manners to goe thy waie, &amp; knock no more. But here behold, God ſtands at the dore of our harts, &amp; giues not three raps onelie, but a fourth too. So that his rule is this:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si ter pulſanti nemo reſpondet, abire</l>
               <l>Non licet, vrgendum eſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Jf after thrice knocking, a man ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not vnto him, yet he will not go awaie, but knock againe; even ſo long, till his head be full of deaw, and his locks with the drops of the night, as it is in the former chapter,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> ſaying, <hi>Open vnto me, my ſiſter, my loue, my doue, my vndefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12298:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And that wee may be able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend with al Saints, what is the <hi>bredth, &amp; length, &amp; depth, &amp; height of his loue,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Eph. 3.18.</note> He cals vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the foure quarters of the earth; there is the <hi>bredth</hi> of his loue: And he cals even thoſe that are <hi>Elongati,</hi> a long way removed from him by their ſins, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.26.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal:</hi> 73. theres the <hi>lengh</hi> of his loue. And he calls vs even from the gates of hell: theres the <hi>depth</hi> of his loue. And he calls vs to returne to himſelfe to heauen theres the <hi>height</hi> of his loue.</p>
            <p>But here J find two <hi>rubbs, or stumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling blocks</hi> in the way, which would firſt be remoued, ere J proceede any further.</p>
            <p>The one, how it is that our Sauiour here calls vs <hi>foure times</hi> to returne, when yet we read it <hi>fiue times</hi> repeated <hi>Amos:</hi> 1. Thus ſaith the Lord.<note place="margin">Amos, 1.3.6.9.11.13.</note> 
               <hi>Super tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſceleribus, et ſuper quatuor, non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertam eum.</hi> For three tranſgreſſions of <hi>Azza,</hi> and for foure, J will not turne to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12298:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>it. The like is there ſaid of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Edom,</hi> and of <hi>the children of Ammon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which place while ſome haue miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnderſtood, they haue not ſtuck erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly to inferr, that if a man offend twice or thrice in the ſame kind, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance may procure him for giuenes: but if he offend a fourth time alſo, his offenſe (ſay they) is vtterly vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable.</p>
            <p>But this doubt wil ſoone be clear'd, this errour ſoone diſpell'd, if the words of the prophet be rightly conſtrued. For there a certaine number is put for an vncerteine, like as here in my text.</p>
            <p>Here's 4 <hi>Returnes for many returnes:</hi> &amp; ſo there 4 <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> or (as ſome will haue it) <hi>7 tranſgreſſions</hi> (becauſe 3 &amp; 4. make 7.) for many <hi>tranſgreſſions.</hi> So that the meaning is, as it the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had ſaid: <hi>If Damaſcus,</hi> if <hi>Azza,</hi> &amp; the reſt of thoſe cities, had tranſgreſſed againſt me by perſecuting my people, only twice, or thrice, J could happily haue borne it: but becauſe they haue
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12298:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>eaſed, but haue perſecuted them even <hi>a fourth or a ſeuenth time,</hi> (that is, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times,</hi>) J wil not turne them vnto me for their amendment, but J will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne them to their confuſion.</p>
            <p>But if with thoſe <hi>heretiks</hi> we ſhould vnderſtand this ſcripture, as if the Lord had ſaid: Three tranſgreſſions J will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, but the fourth I wil not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we make one ſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pture to croſſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict another, ſith we read of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſses,</hi> that he committed both idolatry and murther, more than foure times, &amp; yet he finally obteined remiſſion.</p>
            <p>How be it J deny not, but that as our Sauior ſaith <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. there is a ſin which ſhall neither be forgiuen in this worlde,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.32</note> nor in the world to come, that is, which ſhal neuer be forgiuen, &amp; that is blaſphemie againſt the holy Ghoſt, a ſin not of infirmitie, but of maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And this is that which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt. ca.</hi> 5. cals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> a ſin vnto death: becauſe though death bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the wages not of one,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12298:21"/>but of everie ſin,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. yet the ſin of blaſphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, is by aſpeciall prerogatiue called a ſin vnto death, becauſe it better deſerues his wages, than anie other ſin.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond rub, or ſtumbling block</hi> to be remoued, is this: How it is true, that the holy man <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iob. 33.14.</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 33. <hi>Semel lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur Deus, &amp; ſecundò idipſum non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit:</hi> God ſpeaks once, &amp; repeats it not a ſecond time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet here we ſee our Saviour ſpeaks not once onely, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it a ſecond, third, and fourth time!</p>
            <p>For the clearing of which doubt, we are to note,<note place="margin">Hugo de S. Victor.</note> that (as <hi>Hugo de S. Victore</hi> teacheth) that place of <hi>Iob</hi> muſt thus be vnderſtood: God ſpeakes once for the time of this life, <hi>Praecipiendo, prohiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, promittendo, comminando:</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, by forbidding, by promiſing, by menacing. But in the future life (ſaith he) <hi>Non erit tempus docendi, ſed iudicandi:</hi> It wilbe no time of teaching, but of iudging. Jt is therfore <hi>Verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripartitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a ſpeech of 4 parts, which he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12298:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeakes but once. <hi>Praecipit bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, promittit gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, comminatur paena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth good, hee forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth bad, hee promiſeth glorie, and hee threatneth puniſhment. And yet this foure-parted ſpeech is ſaide to bee but one, becauſe it aimes but at one end which is our conuerſion. His precept teacheth how to partake his promiſe; &amp; his prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how to avoid his threats. But whatſoeuer hee ſhal ſpeake in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, apperteineth not anie waie to converſion, but only to retributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Jt is either <hi>Come ye bleſſed,</hi> or, <hi>Goye curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs therfore while we haue time anſwere this foure-folde ſpeech of his with a foure-fold duty of ours. His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, by our obedience in doing good: his prohibition, by our temperance in abſteining fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evil: his promiſe, by our loue: and his threatnings, by our feare: leſt that place of <hi>Iob</hi> be verified of vs in another ſenſe: according to the original <hi>Quum ſemelloquitur Deus fortis, etiam bis, non cernit illud mortalis.</hi> The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12298:22"/>God ſpeaks once, yea twice, yet ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeth it not that is (as <hi>Tremellius</hi> &amp; <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> expound it) ſuch is the dulneſſe &amp; ſluggiſhnes of our nature,<note place="margin">Tremell.</note> that though God do frequently and fervently ſolicit vs, yet we will not giue him the eare of obedience. He hath healed Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet Babylon will not be healed,<note place="margin">Ierem. 51.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ierem.</hi> 51. Neither will wee returne, though here he bid vs foure times returne.</p>
            <p>But why 4 <hi>times?</hi> J will not bee ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, to ſay, becauſe the number of foure is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a perfect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Met. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> cal'd it <hi>Metap.</hi> 1 Yet becauſe J think it anie thing rather than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a vaine babbling or idle repetition of the ſame words to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (ſuch as our aduerſaries vſe, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a kinde of religion in their ſet nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and other praiers) I would gladlie borrow your honourable &amp; Chriſtian patience, while J gueſſe at ſome reaſons of this foure-fold repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; partly alſo follow the coniectures of others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:12298:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Jt may probably be thought, that he cals vs 4 times becauſe of that foure-fold duty that we ow him: As a <hi>king,</hi> as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> as a <hi>God.</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bute, as a king honor, as a Prieſt loue, as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet feare, as a God. Jf we returne, we pay him tribute; Jf we returne, we doe him honor: Jf we returne, we manifeſt our loue: Jf we returne, wee teſtifie our feare.</p>
            <p>Or, hee cals vs 4 times, becauſe it is not one, but all ages that he cals <hi>child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, youth, middle-age,</hi> &amp; <hi>old-age:</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnder the 4 watches, <hi>Merk.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">Mark. 13 31</note> All haue offended, none is exempted.</p>
            <p>Or 4 times; becauſe hee cals not to one, but to all the 4 <hi>Climats,</hi> &amp; quarters of the worlde: that ſo they may come vnto him, from the <hi>East,</hi> and from the <hi>VVeſt,</hi> from the <hi>North,</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>South,</hi> &amp; ſit downe with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> in the kingdome of God.<note place="margin">Luk. 13.29.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. All which 4 quarters, as they are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the name (the Greeke name) of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Aug. tract. in Joan.</note> (as is noted by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin in Ioan.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12298:23"/>tract.</hi> 9.) the firſt letter (A) ſtanding for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Eaſt:</hi> the ſecond letter (δ) ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the weſt,</hi> the thirde letter (α) ſtanding for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the North:</hi> &amp; the fourth letter (μ) ſtanding for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the South:</hi> So are they likwiſe al of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concluded vnder the nature (the ſinful nature) of <hi>Adam,</hi> and haue therfore all of them need to returne.</p>
            <p>Or 4. times becauſe he cals not with one but 4 voices: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Quadriſonâ voce, per quatuor euangelia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aponius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aponius in Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic.</note>) with a voice of 4 ſounds, the voice of the 4 Euangeliſts; al ſounding a retreit, &amp; calling vs to repentance.</p>
            <p>Which yet is not ſo to be vnderſtood, as if he called vs only with theſe 4 voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin">Auſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> confeſſ. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> For (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> notes <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. c.</hi> 12. <hi>Clamat dictis, factis, morte, vitâ, deſcenſu; a ſcenſu clamat, vt rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus.</hi> He calls vnto vs by his words, by his deeds, by his death, by his life, by his deſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by his aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: By theſe, &amp; many other voices doth he call vs to returne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12298:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Yea and becauſe he knew that one mouth would not be ſufficient, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd the ſcornfull &amp; deriding Jewes, as to make mouths at him, ſo likewiſe to make more mouths in him, <hi>Quot vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, tot ora.</hi> So many wounds, ſo many mouths, calling vs to returne.</p>
            <p>What ſhal J ſay more? Our Sauiour in his commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his diſciples, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. ſaith <hi>Go yee into all the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 16.15</note> 
               <hi>and preach the Goſpell to euery creature: To euery creature,</hi> that is, to man, who is, as it were. A ſhort <hi>Epitome</hi> of all the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God: hauing in him the being of lifeles things: the vegetatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: the ſenſe of beaſts: and the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. But now he giues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature; <hi>Go euery creature,</hi> &amp; preach the Goſpell vnto man. Al the creatures of God are as ſo many preachers, ſo many <hi>Iohn Baptiſts,</hi> ſo many voices of him that crieth in the wildernes of this world: <hi>Returne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 9.28.</note> 
               <hi>Prepareye the way of the Lord by repentance:</hi> as <hi>Exod:</hi> 9. <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>haile</hi> are by an <hi>Hebraiſme</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12298:24"/>the voice of God, calling <hi>Pharao</hi> to returne.</p>
            <p>Or 4 times, becauſe he calls vs, not from one, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 4 <hi>Cardinal vices: Pride, auarice, gluttony, &amp; luxury.</hi> Pride &amp; Auarice care not how vnlawfullly they get and ſcrape together: Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; Luxury, care not how ſhamefully they miſvſe and waſte what is gotten. Jt was pride that lockt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-gates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Lucifer.</hi> Jt was auarice that ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hel-gates to the rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Jt was glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony that turned our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts out of paradiſe. And it is luxury or intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that at this day like a deluge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowes the whole earth.</p>
            <p>Or 4. times (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi>) becauſe he cals vs from a 4-fold pride:<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperbia cordis, ſuperbia oris, ſuperbia operis, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia habitus.</hi> Pride or hart, pride of mouth, pride of worke, &amp; pride of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite. Pride of hart, when a man is great in his owne eies: pride of mouth, when a man not only thinks, but ſpeaks mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifically &amp; highly of himſelfe: pride of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12298:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>worke, when a man not only thinks and ſpeaks prowdly, but his pride breaks forth into action: &amp; pride of habit, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mans pride ſits vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſkirts, &amp; ſhews it ſelfe in the gaudines of his attire.</p>
            <p>Or 4 times (ſaith <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi>) becauſe he cals vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 4 peremptory &amp; dominiering affections,<note place="margin">Hugo Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in Cant.</note> wherewith we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are miſerably wreckt &amp; tortur'd here in this life: <hi>Ioy, ſorrow, feare,</hi> &amp; <hi>hope:</hi> Joie for ſome preſent good, ſorrow for ſome preſent euil, hope of ſome future good, feare of ſome imminent evill.</p>
            <p>Or 4 times (ſaith <hi>Catetan</hi>) as if he had ſaide:<note place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>an.</note> 
               <hi>Revertere relinquendo caecitatem intellect us: revertere relinquendo pravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem affect us: revertere adhaerendo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati: revertere intendendo bonitati.</hi> Returne by forſaking thy blindenes of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: Returne by forgoing thy crookedneſſe of affection: Returne by adhering to the truth: Returne by addicting thy ſelfe to goodnes.</p>
            <p>Or laſtly 4 times (ſaith <hi>Hugo de S. Vict.</hi>) as if he had ſaid;<note place="margin">Hugo de S. Victore.</note> 
               <hi>Reuertere a meis,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12298:25"/>
               <hi>quia mirabilia ſunt: a tuis, quia prau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſunt: a te, quia omnis caro faenum ad me, quia ego ſummum bonum.</hi> Returne from my waies, becauſe they are deep &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy waies, becauſe they are wicked and intolerable: from thy ſelfe, becauſe al fleſh is graſſe: to me, be cauſe J am thy God, thy chiefeſt God.</p>
            <p>Thus our Sauiour Chriſt, who for our ſakes, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to be not only <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri filius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt:</hi> 13.55 <hi>Mare.</hi> 6.3.</note> a Carpenters ſon, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. but <hi>Faber,</hi> a Carpenter, <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. is here (as yee ſee) become <hi>a maker of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otts.</hi> For theſe are indeed the <hi>Chariotts of Iſrael,</hi> or (if you will) <hi>Quadrigae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, the Chariotts of ſaluation;</hi> like that fiery Chariott, wherin <hi>Elias</hi> was taken vp into heauen,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.11.</note> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>O how happy a thing were it for this city, if ſhe were as ful of theſe <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riotts,</hi> as ſhe is not only of materiall coaches and Chariotts, but euen of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall Chariotts: (ſuch as S <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> largely and excellently deſcribes,<note place="margin">Bernard ſerm. <hi>39.</hi> in Cantic.</note> 
               <hi>ſerm:</hi> 39. in <hi>Cantic.</hi>) <hi>Chariotts of malice,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12298:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>&amp; Chariotts of luxury, and Chariotts of couetouſnes:</hi> but J wil only name you their <hi>wheeles,</hi> &amp; their <hi>horſes</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chariot of <hi>malice</hi> runs vpon 4 <hi>wheeles: Cruelty &amp; Impatience; boldnes,</hi> &amp; <hi>impudence:</hi> and it runns very ſwift to ſhed bloud. The <hi>horſes</hi> that draw it are two, &amp; thoſe very light-footed: <hi>Earthly power,</hi> which doth what it luſteth, &amp; <hi>ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular pomp,</hi> which in its doings is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded.</p>
            <p>The Chariott of <hi>luxury</hi> hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 4. wheeles. <hi>Pampering of the belly: pronenes</hi> to venery <hi>gariſhnes of attire:</hi> and <hi>lazines</hi> of body. The <hi>horſes</hi> that drawe it are 2. &amp; they very ſlow. <hi>Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, &amp; Plenty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chariott of <hi>Couetouſnes</hi> hath likewiſe 4. <hi>wheeles: Puſillanimity, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, contempt</hi> of God, &amp; <hi>forgetfulnes</hi> of death: The <hi>horſes</hi> that draw it are 2. and they very iades. <hi>Ropacitas, et</hi> Tenacitas: <hi>Faſt-hauing</hi> &amp; <hi>Faſt-holding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe &amp; the like <hi>chariots</hi> go march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along everie ſtreete of your cittie.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12298:26"/>Wherefore as <hi>Ieremy</hi> wiſheth,<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 9. that his eies were turn'd into a fountaine of teares: ſo my harts deſire vnto God for this cittie is, that her eies were turn'd into a red ſea of teares: that as <hi>Pharao</hi> &amp; al his chariots, were drown'd in the red ſea.<note place="margin">Exod. 14.27</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. ſo the ſpiritual <hi>Pharao,</hi> the Divell, with all theſe his chariots, were drown'd in the red ſea of your teares. For as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith in the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited) <hi>Illi in ſluctibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. ibid</note> 
               <hi>iſti in fletib': marini illi, amari isti.</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian Pharao,</hi> &amp; his chariots, were drown'd in the ſalt waues of the red ſea: And ſo the <hi>ſpiritual Pharao,</hi> &amp; his chariots, muſt be drown'd in the ſalt teares of our eies, that are red with weeping.</p>
            <p>This of the ſecond thing to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Admonition, which was the <hi>Forme,</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The thirde is the <hi>party admoniſhed:</hi> which is the <hi>Shulamite:</hi> or (as others read it) <hi>Sunamite:</hi> or (as others) <hi>Odolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite:</hi> All affording very good matter of inſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12298:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Arboreus</hi> and <hi>Philo</hi> read it <hi>Odollami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arboreus in Cantic. &amp; Philo Carp. Epiſcop.</note> which is expounded, <hi>Teſtimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in aquâ:</hi> A <hi>teſtimony in the water.</hi> A name of fit reſpondence &amp; conſonance, with the Chriſtian ſoule, which being waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cleanſed with the water of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, giues teſtimony in the water to the faith of Chriſt, there confeſſing the trinity in vnitie, and vnitie in trinitie of divine ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, ſhee may be call'd <hi>A teſtimony in the water:</hi> becauſe in the <hi>waters of Marah,</hi> (euen in the bitter waters of repentance) ſhee giues teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of her hartie ſorrow for her ſins: there confeſſing with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.17.</note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24 <hi>Beholde, I haue ſinned, yea I haue done wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This eie-water of repentance is the onely vvater able to quench the fire of concupiſcence in the houſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa <hi>94.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is that <hi>holy-water-ſprinkle</hi> that the Diuell cannot away with. Jt is the <hi>cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalline humour</hi> of the eie of faith. Jt is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12298:27"/>that <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> that muſt reuiue the languiſhing Chriſtian. Jt is that <hi>Aqua caeleſtis,</hi> which God keeps in his flagon, leſt a drop of it ſhould be loſt. Jt is that <hi>brine,</hi> wherewith both fleſh, and ſpirit muſt be kept from tainture, and putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>Jt is (as <hi>Lavater</hi> cals it,<note place="margin">Lavat. hom. <hi>6.</hi> in Ruth.</note> 
               <hi>homil.</hi> 6. <hi>in Ruth</hi>) <hi>ſanguis animae,</hi> the <hi>bloud</hi> (the white bloud) wherin the life of the ſoule conſiſteth.</p>
            <p>Jt is (as <hi>Gregorie Nazanzen</hi> cals it) <hi>orat.</hi> 39. <hi>in Sanct. Lumina</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. orat. <hi>39.</hi> in Sanct. Lum.</note> A <hi>ſecond laver of regeneration,</hi> the onely <hi>rebaptization</hi> allow'd in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie.</p>
            <p>Wherfore <hi>Leo</hi> (in his ſermon <hi>de caen. domin.</hi>) ſpeaking of the teares of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo ſerm. de can. domin.</note> who had grieuouſly ſinned by deny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing his Maſter with an oath: Happie (ſaith he) were thy teares (O thou bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle) <hi>Quae ad diluendam culpam negationis, virtutem ſacramenti habue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt baptiſmi;</hi> which had the efficacy of the Sacrament of Baptiſme, to waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12298:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſinne of thy deniall.</p>
            <p>As is the water of baptiſme to the faithleſſe ſoule, ſo is the water of teares to the faithful. <hi>Peter</hi> was waſht as clean from the ſteine of abnegation with the water of his teares, as was <hi>Paule</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſteine of perſecution with the water of baptiſme. The ſoule then of <hi>Peter</hi> was a good <hi>Odollamite:</hi> For it was, <hi>Teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in aquâ,</hi> A <hi>teſtimony in the water.</hi> His outward teares teſtified his inward ſorrow. His eies were as <hi>cryars</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime his harts-griefe. <hi>Hee went forth and wept bitterly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. till by crying he had outcried the cry of his ſin.</p>
            <p>So the ſoule of <hi>Mary Magdale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was a good <hi>Odollamite:</hi> For it was <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium in aquâ:</hi> A <hi>testimony in the water.</hi> Shee was once poſſeſt with 7 Diuels,<note place="margin">Luk 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. Yet becauſe ſhee waſht not her own face only, but the feete of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour too with her teares,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.38.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. as the queſtion is aſked concerning the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had 7 huſbands,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.87.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>In the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, whoſe ſhall ſhee bee of the 7?</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12298:28"/>So if it be demaunded as touching her, that had 7 Diuels; <hi>In the reſurrection whoſe ſhall ſhee be of the</hi> 7? J anſwere, as there our Saviour doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning that other woman. <hi>Surely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 30.</note> 
               <hi>none of all theirs: but ſhee ſhalbe, and already is, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo muſt we alſo be <hi>Odollamites,</hi> we muſt giue teſtimonie to God in the <hi>waters.</hi> We muſt not thinke to go to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>by land</hi> (as ſome of our great <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded-men</hi> do) but wee muſt paſſe over: <hi>waters</hi> ere we can come thither: The one, the <hi>VVater of baptiſme:</hi> the other, the <hi>VVater of repentant teares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This of the firſt reading <hi>Odollamitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>Sunamitis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronym. Bernard. Rupers. Anſelm.</note> So reads S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ierom,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard, Rupertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Anſelmus,</hi> &amp; diuerſe others, paterning themſelues by the <hi>Greeke</hi> tranſlation of the <hi>ſeptua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint,</hi> and by the <hi>vulgar Latin edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rupertus</hi> and <hi>Anſelmus</hi> expound it <hi>Captiva,</hi> which ſignifieth a ſlaue, or a captiue: as if our Saviour had ſaid: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne (O ſoule) poore ſoule, poorer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12298:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>verie poverty it ſelfe, becauſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels captiue vnder the yoake of ſin.</p>
            <p>For (as <hi>Hugo de</hi> S. <hi>Victore</hi> notes) Three ſtates there are of the faithfull ſoule.<note place="margin">Hugo de S. Victore.</note> Vnder the firſt, ſhee is <hi>Captiva,</hi> a bondwoman: vnder the ſecond, ſhee is <hi>Libera,</hi> a freewoman: vnder the third, ſhee is <hi>Beata,</hi> a bleſſed Saint.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, ſhe is ſubiect to the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of wickednes. In the ſecond, ſhe fighteth vnder the banner of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. In the third, ſhe, hath full fruition of happines.</p>
            <p>As ſhe is a bondwoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is here ſaid vnto her, <hi>Returne, returne ô Sunamite,</hi> that of a bond woman thou maiſt be made free. As ſhe is a free woman, it is ſaid vnto her <hi>Pſal:</hi> 27. <hi>viriliter age.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.16.</note> Play the <hi>virago:</hi> be ſtonge, &amp; let thine hart cheare thee, &amp; put thy truſt in the Lord, that of a free woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou maiſt become bleſſed. As ſhe is in the ſtate of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it is ſaid vnto her,<note place="margin">Pſal. 47.1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. <hi>Cantate domino in Sion.</hi> O ſing vnto the Lorde in <hi>Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> O ſing vnto God with the voice
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12298:29"/>of melody.</p>
            <p>In her firſt ſtate, ſhe is a ſeruant, and feareth. Jn her ſecond ſtate, ſhe is a daughter, &amp; loueth. Jn her third ſtate, ſhe is a ſpouſe, &amp; embraceth.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Hieronym. ad Nepotian</note> 
               <hi>S Ierom</hi> in his epiſtle <hi>ad Nepotianum,</hi> expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds this word <hi>Suna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis, Coccinea:</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen-colourd:</hi> as if our ſauior had ſaid. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, o thou crimſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſcarlet-colourd ſinner. Thou whoſe ſins haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed thee into that colour, which the whore had contracted by ſlaying the Saints of God,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>Apoc:</hi> 17. Jf thou wilt but reuert, &amp; turne from thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed waies, be thy ſins as crimſen, they ſhalbe made white, as ſnow: be they red as ſcarlet, they ſhalbe as wool.<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>I who once in deriſion, was my ſelfe put into a purple robe, J, euen J will caſt thee into a new fatt, &amp; die thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another hew, a hew ſurpaſſing the ſkill of the ſkilfulſt diers. They indeed can cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge a thing into any colour ſaue white: But I, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo deepe a tincture of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12298:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſin, as is crimſen or ſcarlet, will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thee into ſo pure a colour of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, as is white. Thou ſhalt neither be ſo far from a ripe &amp; perfect man in Chriſt, as to be but <hi>greene:</hi> nor ſo fraught, and ouerflowing with the gall of bitternes, as to be <hi>yelow:</hi> nor ſo blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with cruelty, as to be <hi>red:</hi> nor ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with any kind of impiety, as to be <hi>black:</hi> but ſo <hi>ſnow,</hi> ſo <hi>lily-white,</hi> as to ſurmount not the curtines only of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in comelines, but his perſon too in roialty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Lauretus</hi> in his <hi>Sylua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lauret. in Sylod.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds this word <hi>Sunamitis, Dormiens,</hi> or <hi>Iteratio dormitionis,</hi> which ſignifieth A <hi>ſleepe,</hi> or an <hi>Iteration of ſleepe:</hi> as if our Sauiour had ſaid, Returne (ó thou ſleeping &amp; ſlumbring ſoule) thou that every foot falleſt into an heauy ſleepe of ſin, and maiſt therfore wel be cald an <hi>Iteration of ſleepe,</hi> becauſe thy whole life is nothing elſe, but a continuall ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſleepe after ſleepe; O that yet at lengh after ſo many iterations of thy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12298:30"/>ſleepe, thou wouldeſt harken to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iterations of my call.</p>
            <p>For as philoſophy teacheth, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of bodily ſleepe, engendreth three dangerous diſeaſes in the body. The firſt is <hi>Epilepſia, the falling ſicknes.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>Ephialtes, the night-mare.</hi> The third is <hi>Lethargia,</hi> the <hi>diſeaſe of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes:</hi> So the ſleepe of the ſoule (I meane an exceſſiue ſleep in ſin) breeds three no leſſe dangerous diſeaſes in the ſoule, anſwerable to thoſe other three in the bodie.</p>
            <p>THe firſt is <hi>Epilepſia,</hi> the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of, Pride: a diſeaſe that cauſeth a ſwimming and a giddines in the head, and ſo entoxicat's the braine, that oft times it maks a man fall down for dead: according to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. <hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and an high minde before a fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>Ephialtes,</hi> the night-mare of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence: A diſeaſe which makes a man thinke, that he ſeeth an <hi>Old-woman</hi> lying hard vpon him, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12298:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>preſſing him downe, ready to choake, and ſtrangle him. This <hi>old-woman,</hi> is the <hi>fleſh,</hi> which if it be not ſubdued &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by abſtinence, lyeth hard vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule, and preſſeth it down, euen to the pit of hell: according to that of <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sap.</hi> 9. <hi>Corpus quod corrumpitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sap. 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> A corruptible body is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy vnto the ſoule, and the earthly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion keepeth downe the minde that is full of cares.</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>Lethargia,</hi> the lethargie of covetouſnes, which we may rightlie tearme the diſeaſe of forgetfulnes: A diſeaſe that manie times makes a man ſleepe out his life, and die ſleeping. For ſuch, and ſo vnthankful is the nature of couetonſnes, that the more, &amp; greater bleſſings ſhe receiueth of the Lord, the leſſe ſhee remembers them: ſuch, and ſo deadly her ſleepe, that whoſo is once poſſeſſed with it, ſeldome or neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakes, but dies ſleeping: according to that of <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>There is one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>alone, &amp; there is not a ſecond,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12298:31"/>which hath neither ſon, nor brother, yet is there none end of all his trauaile, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can his ey be ſatiſfied with riches, nither doth he thinke, For whome do I trauaile, and defraude my ſoule of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sith then the ſleepe of ſin is ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a ſleepe, <hi>Awake thou that ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and ſtand vp from the dead, &amp; Chriſt ſhall giue thee light,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells thee, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. So ſhalt thou neuer once be troubled,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.14.</note> either with the <hi>Epilepſy</hi> of pride, which was the Diuels ſicknes, or with the <hi>night-mare</hi> of concupiſcence which is the fleſhes ſicknes, or with the <hi>lethargie</hi> of couetouſnes, which is the worlds ſicknes.</p>
            <q>Returne, returne ô Sunamite.</q>
            <p>But here you wil happily demand of me, ſithence this name <hi>Sunamite</hi> is <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men patronymicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a patronimick nowne deriued of the City <hi>Sunam</hi> (a City in the land of promiſe) What <hi>Sunamite,</hi> or what woman of the city <hi>Suna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> it was to whome my text may ſeeme to haue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12298:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>reference.</p>
            <p>Two <hi>Sunamit's</hi> there were, of whom there is honorable mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in the booke of Kings.</p>
            <p>The one, was <hi>Abiſhag,</hi> faire and beautiful Damoſel, which was brought to <hi>King Dauid,</hi> when he was ſtricken in yeares, to cheriſh his old &amp; cold bloud, &amp; to miniſter vnto him: 1. <hi>King.</hi> 1. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 1.4. <hi>Carthuſian. Mercer.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mercer,</hi> and <hi>ſome others,</hi> thinke that alluſion is here made to her.</p>
            <p>The other, was that noble, deuout, &amp; wel diſpoſed <hi>Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 4.8.</note> 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. who gaue ſo kinde welcome to the <hi>Prophet Eliſha,</hi> and that hee might be the more willing to come often to her, prouided him <hi>a chamber, a bed, a table, a ſtoole, &amp; a candleſticke.</hi> The more part of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters thinke that alluſion is here made to her.</p>
            <p>And had God then indeede ſo great rcgard of ſo ſmall a fauor conferred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Prophet? Doth he keep a <hi>Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Regiſter</hi> of her name that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd it? Hath he erected an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12298:32"/>trophae, and moniment therof to all eternitie? Hath he written her name as in heauen (no doubt) ſo in earth too, and that in his owne booke, the <hi>ſacred Bible?</hi> and hath he alſo tranſlated it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Church, calling his Church <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namite?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O come hither, and conſider this, ye that are the great and wealthy ones of this world: yee that haue <hi>Promptuaria plena, eructantia ex hoc in illud,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.13</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. ye that haue the world at will, and your garners, and your ware-houſes, and your counting-houſes full-fraught with all manner of ſtore: vpon whom the Lord of heaven hath heaped earthly treaſures, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a meaſureles meaſure, not that ye ſhould be <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di, Treaſurers &amp; hoard-maſters</hi> to lay them vp, but <hi>Promi, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, and Diſpenſers</hi> to lay them out; ye that ſo loue &amp; long after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your names, that leſt they ſhould die togither with you, ye call &amp; chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten your lands by your owne names;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12298:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>How is it, that loving to haue your names durable, ye loue not to vſe the meanes that ſhould make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> durable? So far (many of you) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the minde of this noble <hi>Sunamite,</hi> that yee count all but loſt, that ye beſtow vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reliefe and maintenance of <hi>Eliſha:</hi> J meane, of the Prophets and Miniſters of God, of religious and learned men.</p>
            <p>Where J cannot but condole the neuer-ſufficientlie deplored eſtate of the <hi>Cleargie:</hi> who when they haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and exhauſted their daies, &amp; their yeares, their ſtrength, and their vigor, their bodies, &amp; their ſpirits, their health and their wealth, and whatſoeuer they either haue, or themſelues are, in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wholſome, &amp; religious ſtudies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable both for Church and Common wealth: yet are faine many times (as a learned writer complaines) <hi>Cum egeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; fame conflictari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melman.</note> to make many a fray with pouertie and hunger. And were it not, that God in ſingular favor to his Church, hath giuen vs a gracious
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12298:33"/>Prince, who is himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, verie learned, and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a lover of learning in others; who himſelfe is truely religious, and therefore a cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of true religion in others, it might iuſtly be feared, that within a while, the ſtate of the Church would be aſmuch to pitied, as is now the ſtate of <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi> when men of the beſt and rareſt gifts, for want of due encouragement, ſhalbe deterred from turning their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors, to the propagating, &amp; adorning of the Church of God: And when they haue ſerued, J ſay not one, or two, but 3 <hi>prentiſhips,</hi> or perhaps, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three, for a <hi>beautifull Rahel,</hi> they are at lengh put ouer to ſome <hi>bleare-eyed Leah</hi> a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſome 20, or 30 pounds a yeare, or perhaps, nor that neither: when <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of Church-liuings,</hi> who are bound in a ſtronger ty of duty, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other men, to be <hi>Sunamit's</hi> to Gods <hi>Eliſha's,</hi> inſteed of finding <hi>Eliſha, a Chamber, a Bed, a Table, a Stoole, &amp; a Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleſtick,</hi> through their indirect, vnconſcionable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12298:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>dealing (maugre all law and ſtatute to the contrary) doe euen ſtifle vp the <hi>Chamber of Eliſha's</hi> hart:<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4. Pſal. 7.6.</note> and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Simony</hi> to ly tumbling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Bed</hi> of his conſcience:<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.23.</note> and make the <hi>Lords table</hi> euen a ſnare vnto him: and allow him no <hi>ſtoole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.20.</note> but the <hi>ſtoole of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi> and doe not giue but ſell him the <hi>Candleſtick of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 2.5.</note> wherin they leaue him only ſome litte <hi>ſnuffe of the liuing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſuch as ſtinks in the noſtrels, both of God and men.</p>
            <p>The verieſt <hi>Corydon, and Lack-latin</hi> that euer ſerued <hi>Cure</hi> for 20. nobles a yeare, let him but haue <hi>Entia,</hi> ſtore of pelf, wherwith to demerit, and win the <hi>Patron,</hi> and it ſki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls not how he be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, either with <hi>Scientia</hi> or <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> with learning, or with honeſty. <hi>Gold &amp; ſiluer,</hi> are more pretious metals tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meane time, they either conſider not, or regard not, that as</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>ſtealer and the receiuer</hi> are theifes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12298:34"/>both ſo the ſelling <hi>Patron,</hi> and buying <hi>Incumbent,</hi> are thieues both. The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron,</hi> becauſe he robbs the Church of her inheritance: and the <hi>Incumbent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he not only peepes in at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow like a <hi>foole, Eccl.</hi> 21. but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creeps in at the window like a <hi>thiefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 21.26. Ioan. 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10. And therfore he had but his right, if with the dogge in the fable, who came in by the window, he were throwne out by the dore.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe cruell and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>Patrons,</hi> who wil ſtill haue vs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to go with <hi>ſhauen crownes,</hi> (not the <hi>Crowns of our heads</hi> after the <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> diſcipline, but the <hi>Crownes of our purſes</hi> after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cutt) Let me tel them, that the money which no leſſe irreligiouſly, than ſacrilegiouſly they get and ſcrape togither by the ſpoile and pillage of the Church, howſoever they may conuert it euen <hi>In pios vſus,</hi> to good and charitable vſes, as to the building or enriching of <hi>Colledges, Schooles, Hoſpitals,</hi> or the like (though
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12298:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is not often ſeene, that money ſo ill-gotten is ſo well beſtowed) yet their purchaſe is no better<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than that which <hi>Iudas</hi> made with the ſilver he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by betrayeng his Maſter,<note place="margin">Act. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 1. wherewith though hee bought a field, then commonly call'd the <hi>Potters field,</hi> and that to no worſe vſe, than to burie ſtrangers in, thinking thereby to haue waſht away the guilt of his treaſon: yet that bloudy &amp; lowd-voiced ſin of his, rung ſuch a peale of vengeance in the eates of the Almightie, yea and was ſo diſtaſtful to the very <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelues, that (God ſo appointing) whereas hee thought to haue purchaſed a glorious name of immortalitie, his purchaſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede was nothing elſe, but an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious name of perpetual obloquy; that very field being to this day call'd <hi>Acel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama,</hi> which, by interpretation, is the field of bloud.</p>
            <p>But ahlas, ahlas (beloued) it is not for me to hope, that J ſhal ever be able as it were with one blaſt of a ſhort, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12298:35"/>weake breath, to blow downe this <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall</hi> and monſtrous ſinne of <hi>Simonie,</hi> which hath enchaunted and empoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oned the whole Realme: And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that ſhee hath often ben even crucified and nayl'd to this verie <hi>Croſſe</hi> with the <hi>hammer</hi> of Gods <hi>word,</hi> as <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Iere. 23.29.</note> c. 23. yet for all that goeth ietting it vp and down, as freſh and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, as luſtie and liuely in euery part of this land, as if ſhee had neuer ben toucht or talkt of: her ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t being of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> her <hi>brow</hi> of <hi>braſse,</hi> and her <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>ſilver and gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore leauing her as deſperate as J found her, J will now come a little nearer home to this cittie. A citty, as for wiſdome another <hi>Grece,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lipſ. de Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. b. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> cals <hi>Sal &amp; Solgentium:</hi> the ſalt and the ſun of other nations; So for plentie another <hi>Sicily,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aret. Chorog Sicil.</note> which <hi>Aretius</hi> cals <hi>Cell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> penuaria,</hi> the <hi>ſtore-houſe;</hi> or (it ye will) <hi>Mamma,</hi> the <hi>teat</hi> or <hi>breſt,</hi> whereou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many other places ſuck no ſmal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:12298:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A city, which J know (&amp; the <hi>Colledge</hi> Wherof I am, muſt thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) is the mother of manie a good <hi>Sunamite,</hi> many that are ſincerelie and hartilie deuoted to learning and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And yet (not ſo flatter her) the Lord hath a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſie with manie her rich pinch-peny &amp; cloſe-fiſted inhabitants: whoſe charitie is ſo benumm'd and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, that as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of himſelfe in another caſe:<note place="margin">Pſal 119.</note> 
               <hi>Factus ſum ſicut vter in pruinâ:</hi> J am become like a bottle in the froſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. ſo it may be truelie alſo ſaid of them, that they are become like a frozen bottle. They hold al in, &amp; let nothing run out.</p>
            <p>They haue withered hands, like the hand of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 13.7</note> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 13. and till it pleaſe the Lorde in mercie to reſtore them, they cannot once ſtretch them out to giue a reward to Gods Prophet.</p>
            <p>And as an ouen, though the belly of it be ful of loafes, yet the mouth of it is ſtil gaping til it be ſtopt with clay: So
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12298:36"/>they albeit they haue loafes their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ful (by loafes, J meane all temporal bleſſings) yet they are ſtil gaping after more and more gaine, and neuer lin ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, till their mouths bee ſtopt with claie.</p>
            <p>There are others, that are franke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in their ſpending, but yet <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha's</hi> ſhare is leaſt in their expenſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laertius</hi> in the life of <hi>Crates</hi> the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Laert. in vit. Cratet Theb.</note> tels of a memorable <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>day-booke,</hi> wherein that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher had ſet downe the <hi>accounts</hi> of a great rich man: which <hi>accounts</hi> hee there recites to haue ben theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c:</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inprimis</hi> for my <hi>Cooke.</hi> ten pounds.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item</hi> for my <hi>Phyſition.</hi> foure pence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item</hi> for my <hi>Flatterer.</hi> v. talents.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> for my <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailor.</hi> a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of ſmoak.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item</hi> for my <hi>VVhore.</hi> a talent.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> for my <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> 3. halfe-pence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Pardon me <hi>(deare Chriſtians)</hi> if J be iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ouer you with a godly iealouſie. J feare, there are ſome ſuch rich men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12298:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this cittie, whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke,</hi> if a man could come to pervſe, he ſhould finde, if not the ſame, yet the like accounts. Jt grieues them not to be at coſt, with their <hi>Cookes,</hi> their <hi>flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> and their <hi>whores,</hi> ten or twentie pounds thicke: but <hi>Phyſitions, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> and <hi>learned Divines,</hi> O its mony welſpared, that is not ſpent vpon them.</p>
            <p>J know not, whither there bee anie place for perſwaſions in the hearts of thoſe, that are already ſo fully preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied with indevotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Notwithſtanding, either (if it may bee) to reclaime them, or (if not) at leaſtſwiſe to leaue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, J hold it my duty to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them of <hi>another,</hi> and that a <hi>ſtricter account,</hi> to which when God ſhal ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon them vpon that great and general <hi>audit-day</hi> of iudgement, they will both ſhame and tremble to giue vp ſuch an account as this.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, of that amiable <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.41.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. that not ſo ſmal a kindnes as a cup of cold water
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12298:37"/>beſtowed vpon a Prophet in the name of a Prophet ſhal paſſe vnrewarded.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, of <hi>foreine examples</hi> of our <hi>Antichriſtian adverſaries,</hi> vvho prouide ſo liberally for the Miniſters of Antichriſt, that they haue not onelie wherewith richlie to finde themſelues, but ouer and aboue, wherewith to fee their drabs, to feed their hounds, and to fleſh their horſes: when yet many of the poore and true Miniſters of Chriſt, haue not wherwith to buy them meate for their belly, cloathes for their backe, or bookes for their ſtudie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, &amp; laſtly, of <hi>ancient exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> regiſtred in holy writ, and left vpon recorde for a paterne of imitation to al ſucceeding ages. As namely, of that <hi>poore widdow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 12.42</note> 
               <hi>Mark.</hi> 12. whoſe 2. ſmall mites which freely and cheerefully ſhe caſt into the treaſury, were accepted of God, as a great largeſſe, and with him were more current, than al that al the rich men of their abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance caſt in: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> notes,<note place="margin">Ambr lib. <hi>1</hi> de vid.</note> 
               <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>de vid.</hi>)
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12298:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>vberior est nummus ex parvo quàm the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus ex maxime.</hi> A penie or halfe-pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of that little which a poore man hath, is more in Gods reckoning, than a whole maſſe of monie out of a rich mans treaſure.</p>
            <p>Of that other <hi>widdow of Zarepta,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17. who becauſe ſhe entertained the prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> in the time of drowth and dearth,<note place="margin">1 King. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> her handful of meale in the barrel, and her little oile in the crewſe, by ſpending was not ſpent, neither any whit diminiſht, till the tyrannie of that dearth were overpaſt.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Gaius,</hi> whome for his loue &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Church &amp; him, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>Hoſpes meus, et vniuerſae Eccleſiae:</hi> his hoſte, &amp; the hoſte of the whole Church <hi>Rom:</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.23 Mat. 26.13.</note> who becauſe ſhe loued much, and powred out the box of pretious oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head of Chriſt, her name is as an o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntment powrd out perſuming the whole houſe, &amp; (as our Sauiour proteſteth, <hi>Mat</hi> 26.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12298:38"/>wherſoeuer this Goſpel ſhalbe preacht throughout al the world, there ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo this that ſhe hath done beſpoken of, for a memoriall of her.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, of this glorious &amp; worthy <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmite,</hi> who for her good deuotion, &amp; reſpectfull vſage of <hi>Eliſha</hi> the prophet of the Lord, is here remembred in her owne name, but yet in another perſon, the perſon of the Church.</p>
            <p>And albeit the Church (euen the ſinful members of the Church) be here called by the name of <hi>Sunamite,</hi> yet is it not that the <hi>Sunamite</hi> ſhould therby be diſhonored, by giuing her name to ſo ſinfull a perſon, but that ſo ſinfull a perſon ſhould the rather be allured, by this kinde and honorable name of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This of the ſecond reading, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Greeke ſeptuagint,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sunamite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is <hi>Shulamitis:</hi> ſo reads S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. Ludov. Soto. Tremell.</note> 
               <hi>Ludouicus Soto, Tremellius, &amp; lunius,</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh Geneua</hi> with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12298:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome others deriuing their tranſlation from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> fountaine.</p>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his oration <hi>de obitu Valentiniani,</hi> expounds it <hi>Pacifica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. orat. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obit. Valent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Quiet, or Peaceable: &amp; it is a <hi>patrony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick nowne</hi> (as was <hi>Sunamite</hi>) deduced of <hi>Shalem,</hi> the ancient name of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which alſo ſignifieth <hi>Peace.</hi> And therfore it is ſaid <hi>pſal:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.2.</note> 76. At <hi>Shalem</hi> is his tabernacle: where the <hi>vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> reads: <hi>In pace factus eſt locus eius:</hi> where peace is, there delights God to dwell.</p>
            <p>When therfore our Sauiour calls his Church <hi>Shulamite,</hi> it is as if he had ſaid: O thou <hi>Daughter of peace,</hi> or O thou <hi>Queene of Shalem, Queene of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Queene of Peace,</hi> becauſe my daughter, and my ſpouſe, who am king of <hi>Shalem,</hi> king of <hi>Ieruſalem, Prince of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, this ſhould teach vs <hi>(my deare &amp; Chriſtian brethren)</hi> that we muſt be <hi>Shalemites,</hi> or <hi>Shalamti's</hi> men of peace and tranquillity, not of diſcord and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12298:39"/>diuiſion.</p>
            <p>It is the factious nature of that old make-bate <hi>Satan,</hi> with all his <hi>Imps,</hi> and impious adherents, to ſtirr vp ſtrife all the day long, and therfore his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is <hi>Malè diuiſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> a diuided King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>Matt:</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.26.</note> But our peace-maker Chriſt, left a great legacy of peace to his Church,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oan 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>peace,</hi> &amp; <hi>his peace, Ioan:</hi> 14. &amp; therfore his kingdome is <hi>Benè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctum:</hi> an vnited kingdome, keeping the vnity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>If then we will haue Chriſt to our father, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Pacificus:</hi> a <hi>cheife Iuſtice</hi> of peace, or a <hi>peace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker:</hi> &amp; the Church to our mother, who is alſo <hi>pacifica, a peace-maker,</hi> we muſt nor proceed <hi>A benè coniuncto ad malé diuiſum:</hi> from the <hi>Sion</hi> of peace to the <hi>Babylon</hi> of confuſion: but we muſt be <hi>Pacifici,</hi> peace-makers, and at peace: A threefold peace. <hi>At peace with God, at peace with our ſelus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernard. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. omn. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; at peace one w another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:12298:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But wee muſt firſt be at <hi>peace with God</hi> by a true converſion, becauſe our peace with him, is the roote of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two-fold peace.</p>
            <p>We muſt not (if we wilbe the ſpouſe of Chriſt) bee ſo head-long and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong in our iniquities, as if by our cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſcowling ſins, we meant to chide and raile him out of his owne houſe, or (as once before) we did to hale him out of heauen, &amp; naile him to the Croſſe, &amp; crucifie again the Lord of life: for then (aſſure we our ſelues) he wil neuer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vs. No; the God of peace loues his peace too well, to mary an vnquiet &amp; a ſcowling wife. Nay, he wil be ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marying vs, that he wil arme al his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures with vengeance to perſecute vs. He will ſharpen his fierce wrath for a ſword, &amp; the world ſhal fight with him againſt the vnwiſe, as the wiſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeaks <hi>Sap.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Sap: 5.20.</note> Neither ſhal that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ever haue <hi>Pacem a ſepte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpiritibus,</hi> peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 7 ſpirits which are before the throne of God, ſpoken of <hi>Apoc:</hi> 1,<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.4.</note> who hath
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12298:40"/>
               <hi>Pacem cum ſepte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpiritibus,</hi> peace with the ſeauen vncleane ſpirits, ſpoken of, <hi>Matt:</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.45.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if laying aſide our former ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, we returne to God, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Shulamits</hi> at peace with him, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil he betroath and mary vs vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as he promiſeth <hi>Oſe:</hi> 2. <hi>I will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thee vnto me for ever:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſe. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>yea I will mary thee vnto me in righteouſnes &amp; in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; in mercy, and in compaſsion. I will euen mary thee vnto me in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; thou ſhalt knowe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt be <hi>Shulamits, at peace with our ſelues,</hi> by an inward peace of conſcience. For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conveniet nulli,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat.</note> 
               <hi>qui ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſsidet ipſe.</hi> Hee that cannot agree with himſelfe, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil he agree? As we muſt not haue <hi>a weight &amp; a weight</hi> in our ſhops: ſo neither muſt wee haue a <hi>worde, and a worde,</hi> in our lips. We muſt not haue 2 <hi>faces</hi> vnder one hood, like <hi>Ianus:</hi> nor 2 <hi>tongues</hi> in one head, like <hi>Iudas;</hi> nor 2 <hi>harts</hi> in one breſt, like <hi>Peter:</hi> but wee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12298:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt be <hi>Vnus, non Plures: ſingular,</hi> not <hi>plurall: one,</hi> and <hi>not many.</hi> For (as the Apoſtle tels vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.24</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Vnus accipit brauium:</hi> One receiueth the price. <hi>One?</hi> who is that <hi>one?</hi> Not ſuch a one as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades,</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Aemilius Prob'</hi> writes:<note place="margin">Aemil. Prob. in vit. Alcib.</note> 
               <hi>Nihilillo fuiſſe excellentius, velin vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs, vel in virtutibus:</hi> that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in both kindes, good &amp; bad: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently virtuous, and excellently viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: <hi>vt omnes admirarentur in vno ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine tantam ineſſe diſsimilitudinem, tam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diverſam naturam:</hi> ſo that al men wondred that there ſhould bee in one man ſuch diſparitie, ſuch diverſity of nature.</p>
            <p>Not ſuch a one as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeaks of writing vpon <hi>Leuiticus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen. in Levitic.</note> 
               <hi>Agnoſce in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus Chamaeleonte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> There are ſome (ſaith he) iuſt like the <hi>Chamaeleon.</hi> For as the <hi>Chamaeleon</hi> is very eaſily changed into whatſoeuer colour almoſt is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: ſo there are many that deſiring to pleaſe al, do conforme and faſhion themſelues to the wils of al: &amp; becauſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12298:41"/>they feare al colours, wil eaſily be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd into any colour: <hi>Cum iraſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus iraſcuntur, detrahunt cum detrahe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus. &amp;c.</hi> Are others angry? So are they. Do others back-bite? So do they. Do others diſcommend? ſo do they. Do others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend? ſo do they. And (with reuerence be it ſpoken to the words of the Apoſtle) they become all things to al men, that by al meanes they may cozen ſome.</p>
            <p>In a word, not ſuch a one, ſuch a monſter <hi>Holkot</hi> ſpeakes of,<note place="margin">Holkot. lect. <hi>211.</hi> in Sap.</note> 
               <hi>lect:</hi> 211. <hi>in Sap:</hi> that is <hi>Homo per naturam, Daemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per ſuperbia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, taurus per luxuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> A man by nature, a Divel by pride, and a Bull by laſciuiouſnes: but ſuch a <hi>one,</hi> whoſe ſoule is another <hi>Ieruſalem, as a city that is at vnity in it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Quomodo vnus eſt, qui nunc laeti, nunc triſtis, nunc irati vultum, nunc le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, nunc avarri, nunc luxurioſicor habet?</hi> How is he one (ſaith <hi>Hugo</hi>) or how is he at peace with himſelfe,<note place="margin">Hugo de S. Victor.</note> that is one while pleaſant, another while penſiue?
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12298:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>one while angry, another while calme? one while couetous, another while lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurious? <hi>In quo tot perſonae, quot mores:</hi> whoſe perſon is as manifold as his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: &amp; ſo he makes himſelfe a <hi>Lunatik fool: for a foole is variable as the moone: Eccl:</hi> 27. which though ſhee be but one in ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Eccl. 27.11.</note> yet by meanes of her ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> change, is neuer like her ſelfe. Yea, ſo he mak's himſelfe the <hi>Diuels vaſsal,</hi> who as he cals himſelfe <hi>Legio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> becauſe he is many <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. ſo they that are his ſlaues &amp; vaſſals,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.30.</note> howſoeuer they may ſeem to be but one, yet indeed they are not one but many: yea their owne <hi>Conſcience</hi> is both the <hi>Accuſer, &amp; the Accused: the VVitneſse, &amp; the Conuinced: the Iudge, &amp; the Condemned the Hangman, &amp; the Tormented: the Hell, and the Damned.</hi> But on the otherſide, they that are the ſeruants of Chriſt, are not only each in themſelues one, hauing within them a ſweete melody &amp; peace of conſcience: but they are alſo all of them together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e: One by vnanimity, not by vnity of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12298:42"/>perſon. For al that are in Chriſt are but as one,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28. Act. 4.32.</note> 
               <hi>Gal:</hi> 3, as it is ſaid of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>Act:</hi> 4. that they had all but one hart, &amp; one ſoule.</p>
            <p>We muſt therfore, in the third place, be <hi>Shulamits,</hi> at <hi>peace with others,</hi> by an outward peace of Conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauing peace with all men, as the Apoſtle wils vs:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.18 <hi>Carthuſian.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rom:</hi> 12. that is (ſaith <hi>Charthuſian</hi>) a true, and a ſpirituall peace, not a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and a ſecular peace. For our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tels vs <hi>Matt:</hi> 10. that he came not to put this peace vpon the earth,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.34.</note> but a ſword. <hi>A</hi> ſword, to arme the ſon againſt the father, &amp; the daughter againſt her mother, &amp; the daughter in law againſt her mother in law. Not that he would ſimply &amp; without exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue theſe to be at variance each with other (as <hi>Theophylact</hi> wel obſeru's) but to teſtifie vnto vs,<note place="margin">Theophylact</note> that ſuch is his iealouſly of his owne honor, that though he haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs to <hi>honor our father &amp; mother, Exod:</hi> 20. yet if father or mother,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xod. 20.13.</note> kiffe or kin ſhall intend his diſhonor, it is no
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12298:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſhonor for a man, nay rather it is the honor of a man, (&amp; the harder it is, the more honor it is) ſo vnpartially to put by all by-reſpects of nature, as for the honor of God our ſupernal &amp; ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall father, to diſhonor our deareſt naturall friends.</p>
            <p>And ſith we are rather to forſake our ſelues than Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. &amp; the loue of our ſelu's muſt be the rule &amp; meaſure of our loue to others: (for we are to loue our neighbour as our ſelues,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.19.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. As ourſelues, and not as God, for we are to loue God more than ourſelues) what more can our beſt friends expect at our hands, than that if the caſe ſtand betwixt God and them, ſo that of the two one muſt needs be relinquiſht, we ſhould rather relinquiſh any, or al of them than God, who wilbe vnto vs <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus inſtar omnium.</hi> One for al, nay, One better than al, becauſe <hi>All-ſufficient.</hi> And as himſelfe pronounceth of them that doe the wil of his father,<note place="margin">Mark. 3.35.</note> 
               <hi>Marc.</hi> 3. that they are his <hi>brother, &amp; ſiſter, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12298:43"/>mother:</hi> ſo if any do the wil of his father, he is their brother, &amp; ſiſter, &amp; mother, and what not, that elſe can once be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired?</p>
            <p>Gods altar is like <hi>Hercules</hi> his pillar. The Inſcription therof is <hi>Non vltrà.</hi> Our peace may reach thitherto, but no further.</p>
            <p>Wherfore as <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> ſaid of his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Plato;</hi> ſo muſt wee of our beſt and neareſt friends: Though <hi>Plato</hi> be my good friend, yet truth is my better friend, &amp; therfore if <hi>Plato</hi> giue his fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to truth, then farewel <hi>Plato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are not then <hi>(my deare &amp; Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian brethren)</hi> we are not to taxe and cenſure our godly, zealous, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous magiſtrats, as tyrannical, cruel, and vncharitable, if as <hi>Iacob</hi> tooke <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heele,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.26</note> 
               <hi>Gen:</hi> 25. ſo they take the <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> and Sons of <hi>Eſau, (the Papiſts)</hi> ſworne enimies to the truth of Chriſt; crying, as did thoſe <hi>Edomits</hi> in the day of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Downe with it, downe with it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> even to the ground, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 137. &amp;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12298:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>lay them faſt by the heels, who ſo long as they are ſufferd to walke at large, are continvally kicking againſt Gods true religion, ſo happily eſtabliſhed in the dayes of <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> our late ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne of bleſſed memory, and now (bleſſed be God, whoſe bleſſing it is) ſo faithfully continued in this our Realme vnder the raigne of <hi>King Iames,</hi> her rightful and moſt renowned ſucceſſor: who as he hath already peaceably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined the 2 neighbour-kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> concluding both vnder the name of <hi>Great Britaine:</hi> ſo there is nothing (ſay miſdeeming <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents</hi> what they wil) there is nothing that he ſo vehemently deſireth, as the vniting of thoſe other 2 kingdomes, the <hi>kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>kingdome of Antichriſt,</hi> by reducing and bringing backe to the ſheepefold of Chriſt, the Greate ſhepheard and Biſhop of our ſouls, thoſe ſilly wandering ſheepe that ſo long haue ſtraied vpon the 7 moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:12298:44"/>
Which religious work of his would (doubtleſſe) proſper the better in his hands, and take a much more ſpeedie effect, were it not that <hi>Iannes</hi> alſo, and <hi>Iambres</hi> reſiſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> were it not that the home-borne contentions of our mutinous, turbulent, and dogmatical <hi>Noveliſts,</hi> are too-too-high-handed: &amp; that the ſoule of the <hi>Church</hi> is troubled <hi>Propter quadrigas Aminadab,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>chariots</hi> of her voluntarie, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling people,<note place="margin">verſe 11. <hi>Caietan.</hi>
               </note> as it is in the verſe next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my text. J ſay not (as <hi>Caietan</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds that place) by reaſon of the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who perſwaded the <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue</hi> to crucifie our Savior Chriſt: but by reaſon of the true <hi>heires</hi> &amp; <hi>ſucceſsors</hi> of the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes;</hi> who may rightly be called <hi>chariots,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they draw the people which way they luſt: &amp; the <hi>Chariots of Aminadab,</hi> which ſignifieth, <hi>Populus meus ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus,</hi> my readie or willing people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the people are (many of them) as willing to be led, as they to lead them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:12298:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Theſe <hi>Chariots</hi> as they are drawne a maine vvith the <hi>wilde-horſes</hi> of their owne head-ſtrong fanſies: ſo doe they alſo draw whole multitudes after them, and lead captiue ſimple women laden with ſinne, and groſſlie abuſe the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of manie honeſt and well-mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſtians, to their own adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage.</p>
            <p>Theſe be they, that wil not ſuffer the <hi>Church</hi> to ſleepe, nor the <hi>Heades of her Temples</hi> (her <hi>Reverend and learned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats</hi>) to take any reſt, vnleſſe they firſt put of their ſeemelie and decent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their ſurpliſſe, cope, cap and all, to them.</p>
            <p>J wil not ſay (as perhaps J truelie might) that their fond and new-found opinions, are Sathans bals of wilde-fire vvherevvith they haue ſet on fire the Church of God,<note place="margin">Valer. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (as <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> fired the temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> only to get him a name, though it were but a bad one) &amp; that the ſmoake of this their fire hath cauſed manie vveeping eies in the Church of God;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:12298:45"/>
Nor wil J liken them to a man (ſuch a one as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes of in his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations</hi>) ſet vpon the pinnacle of a temple,<note place="margin">Bernard. declamat.</note> and with open mouth greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſucking in the aire, and leſt it ſhould not come faſt enough of it ſelfe, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and gathering it to him <hi>Flabello,</hi> with a fan, <hi>Ac ſi totum ſperaret aërem deglutire:</hi> as if hee meant to drinke vp the whole element of aire: and yet it is thought that their chiefeſt aime, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aura popularis,</hi> the breath of the people, or <hi>Aurum populare,</hi> the wealth of the people;</p>
            <p>Nor would J wiſh them, for breaking the peace of the Church, to be thruſt into a <hi>Iakes,</hi> there to end their daies, as <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Andr: Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorff: in Theatr. hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>and Abundius</hi> were by <hi>Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an quod Sanctae Concordiae corpus è tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo extraxiſſent:</hi> becauſe they had ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Image of Concorde</hi> out of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: But yet thus much J wil be bold to tel them, that they are too-too-like <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Alexandrinus in Suidas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suidas hiſt.</note> who (as he ſaith) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12298:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>he was very il ſpoken of, not becauſe he was greatlie iniurious to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, but becauſe hee was very much giuen to contention: &amp; that they liue ſo vnpeaceably in the Church of Chriſt, as if Chriſt had died inteſtate, &amp; left no <hi>legacy</hi> of peace to his Church:</p>
            <p>Yea (more than this) in Chriſts ſted, for Chriſts ſake, and for their own ſake, and for the Churches ſake, in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of our bleſſed Saviour, J hartilie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech them, that they would ſee euen in this their day, the things that belong vnto their peace: that if by ſtudiouſnes of peace, they wil not turne their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets into bee-hiues (as it is in the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem:</hi>) yet by furiouſnes of rage againſt the diſcipline of the Church, they would not turne the Church (the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of ſaluation,) into a neſt of waſpes: that as <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> is ſaid,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium loco deturbâſſe,</hi> to haue diſplaced bluſtering <hi>March,</hi> which before vvas the firſt moneth, <hi>et primas Iano detuliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, ut pote Pacifico,</hi> and to haue placed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12298:46"/>peaceable <hi>Ianus</hi> in his roome: ſo they would prefer peace before diſcord, and <hi>contentation</hi> before <hi>contention.</hi> Laſtly, that as the <hi>Crete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> who before were at ciuil warre among themſelues, yet when an enemie inuaded them, they would ceaſe to haue edge one againſt another, &amp; iointly band themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Common enemy,</hi> (which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of theirs was therevpon prouerbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the ioining of the Cretenſians:</hi>) ſo vnleſſe they will be worſe than <hi>evill beaſts</hi> (for ſo the <hi>Crete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> are call'd out of one of their owne Poëts,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.) They would lay aſide their ciuil, or rather their vnciuill war, and ioine both harts &amp; hands with vs, againſt thoſe two mightie enemies of the Church <hi>Papiſts, and Atheiſts:</hi> who like the <hi>Mirmaide,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Dolphin,</hi> take their paſtime in the troubled vvaters, while the ſhip of the Church is beaten, and toſſed, and torne aſunder with a tempeſt.</p>
            <p>Thus farre haue our <hi>Noveliſts</hi> (the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12298:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>chariots of the people</hi>) drawne me. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py now, &amp; thrice-happy ſhould J think my ſelfe, if as the Prophet <hi>Ezechtel</hi> in his viſion, ſaw <hi>Rota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in rotâ:</hi> One wheele in another wheele;<note place="margin">Ezech. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1. So J might ſee <hi>Currum in curru:</hi> one <hi>chariot</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>chariot;</hi> to wit, theſe <hi>chariots</hi> of the people in this <hi>chariot</hi> of repentance wherin our Saviour Chriſt would draw al men vnto him, iterating and reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his <hi>Admonition:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Returne, returne ô Shulamite: returne, returne.</q>
            <p>J ſhould now proceede to the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the <hi>Admonition,</hi> including (as J told you) a three-fold promiſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That we may behold thee:</hi> that is, That my Father, my ſelfe, and the holy Ghoſt may caſt a favourable aſpect on thee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>that we may behold thee:</hi> that is, That my ſelfe with the reſt of thy friends &amp; wel-willers, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſociety of Angels may reſpect thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:12298:47"/>
Thirdly, <hi>That we may behold thee;</hi> that is, That both J thy redeemer may looke vpon thee with a fatherly and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate ey of mercy: &amp; that thou maiſt alſo looke into thy ſelfe with a ſyncere, and ſingle eie of ſimplicity.</p>
            <p>But neither wil my out-worn ſtrength giue leaue, nor the time (which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy paſt it's limits) permit, nor (J think) the repining of your bellies ſuffer me, to enter vpon ſo copious a diſcourſe, as this <hi>triple Reaſon</hi> woulde require. Here therfore J make my ful period.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you throughout, &amp; I pray God that your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and body, may be kept blameleſſe vnto the coming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> To whom, with the father, &amp; the holy Ghoſt, one immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, inuiſible, only wiſe, &amp; al good God, in perſon three, in eſſence one, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all power, dominion, and Maieſty both now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12298:47"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
